[repetitive atmospheric music]
[computer wave beeping]
[tires screeching]
[synthesizer beeping]
[computer wave beeping]
[computer beep]
[band playing melodic computer music]
Here.
Here you go.
[repetitive mysterious music]
[electric sparking]
[intensifying electic sizzles]
[pops and extinguisher whooshing]
[audience gasping]
[driving rock music]
Wait.
I think we need to invest in a printer.
What do we need that for?
I thought we could print out some of the
programs and sell them at the merch table
or maybe use them as inserts
for the next album.
Plus, we're gonna need a faster computer.
I've got one of mine that's going to
give us enough juice to be able to run
all the visualization programs we need.
Speaking of which, I don't know if
you saw what happened out there, but-
Listen dude, I don't even want to know.
The band needs to conserve money.
We can't just keep paying
for computer expenses.
But this is important.
There's something very weird going on
here. It's very counterintuitive.
Listen dude, we can't just fund your
computer hobby. We got to do what makes
sense for the band, and our music's
the main focus.
So what are you saying?
Listen dude, we can try to scrape some
money together to get some replacement
parts, but we can’t just get a whole new
computer or a printer.
We barely have enough money
to get from gig to gig.
[band members partying]
[concert-goers laughing]
[birds chirping]
[construction sounds]
[suitcase thump]
[pages flipping]
Hello? Yes, I'm calling for a bed tonight.
Your ad says you have a computer.
[mystical atmospheric music]
I'm on the east side of the city right
now, so I won't be there until later.
What's the best way to get there?
[RV engine guzzling]
[water trickling]
[zipper zipping]
[man grunting]
[Italian] Keys... Room 13.
[Italian] Thank you.
[Italian] You're welcome. Bye.
Hi.
How can I help you?
I called earlier today about a bed.
Oui, Oui... Of course. And how many
nights will you be staying with us?
Indefinitely.
Indefinitely?
[TV news reporting on rioting]
Voila.
Your bed is the left top bunk.
There she is.
[French] Ah, the computer?
The computer is only available
a little while longer.
Hey, what you got going on here?
Appalachian Trail.
Hmm.
You will let me know when
the check arrives?
Umhmm.
Sergey, just for to know, I let the guy
in the left top bunk in the lounge
stay on credit for a couple of days,
just until he gets paid.
Okay, but you know what happened the
last time you were so generous, right?
I know. I know.
I hope I do not regret.
Okay.
I'm showing Francois here his new room.
[French] Is there a problem?
[French] Yes, a guy is smoking in my room.
Everything smells like smoke.
[French] I'm sure your new
room will be much better.
See you.
[mysterious tone]
Something very weird going on here.
I thought it might have been a bug
or something, but I guess not.
What? Why did this stop my game?
Do you see a pattern?
Because I don't.
I see lots of complexity, but...
I want to use the computer.
Okay, just watch this.
I want to show you why this is crazy.
Simple pattern, right?
How about this?
Simple again.
Well, makes sense.
We have a simple program.
How about another?
Okay, this one's a little bit more
intricate than before, but it's still
just a nested pattern with regularity.
Okay, one more.
This one is even more trivial.
But wouldn't you expect that with such a
simple program? But now watch this.
Some patterns on the side here.
But lots of complexity...
Complexity. Complexity...
It's all coming from these very simple
rules. It looks almost random, but...
I'm not sure what's going on here.
It's very weird, very counterintuitive.
Well, don't you see?
Excuse me, I'm very sorry, but
we have to stop the computer now
because the upstairs lounge
is closing early for Yiwen... I'm sorry.
Could you just give us a few more minutes?
We're right in the middle of something
big here. Wouldn't you say?
The downstairs pub and lounge is still
available if you want, but this computer
needs to stop when this lounge closes.
It's the rules.
Okay. Come on, let's go.
[computer power button click]
So what room are you in?
Ah, it's ahh... Walk, umm...
Oh, come on.
[Russian mumbling]
[surprised sound]
[sheets whoosh]
[bed creaking]
Sorry.
[snoring]
[mysterious music]
[door creaking]
Aaaaahhh!
[objects clattering]
It's...  it's not in here.
[dog barking]
[cash register processing]
[food package sliding]
[heavy keystrokes]
[computer wave beeping]
[oud plucking music]
[silverware clanging]
Bonjour.
Hello.
Oh, hey.
You were...
What were you doing last night?
Oh, that. I'm sorry. I just had to
run a few programs, that's all.
Programs. You mean computer?
Well, yeah... I did a systematic search of
all these three-bit, one-dimensional, cell
progression programs. You see, there's
only 256 of them, so it's manageable.
I thought I saw this unique anomaly in one
of the programs, but then I saw another,
something even more interesting.
You know, hold on. It'd be easier to
explain if you could just see what
I'm talking about.
Hey. Hey.
There's a sign-up sheet at the bar, mate.
Just give it a second.
Mate, I saw you bossing the guy around
[computer powering up]
on the computer last night.
Jacqueline's not going to let you stay
here long with that kind of attitude.
You work here?
No, but I've lived here for three years,
so I know how things operate.
All right, well, just give it a second
to print out and it's all yours.
[French] Your days are numbered.
Impressive.
[ba-dum ching keystroke]
[printer printing]
[travelers chatting]
[computer music]
Okay, so this is rule 244,
or 11110100 in binary.
So I printed off the first page which has
the beginning of the program here,
and then a portion of the output
around 10,000 steps in.
Up top are the rules.
For the initial conditions,
I set all the cells to off
except the one in the middle there.
Okay, simple initial conditions,
simple rules... simple result?
No. Look at this complexity.
But wouldn't you expect with such a simple
rule we'd get boring, predictable results?
I don't know.
I mean, that's what I thought. Then I saw
rule 120. That's what brought me here.
I thought it was a mistake, but it's not.
I checked it on the computer. And after
I saw it was a real computational
phenomenon, I had to run all 256 programs
of the same type last night. And then I
ran into this one. And now I'm thinking
that maybe other simple programs
also exhibit this phenomenon.
It's not just these three-bit
cell progression programs.
Well, I...
I'm not sure if I understand what you're
saying, but it sounds interesting.
It's going to take too long.
This kind alone is gonna be 2^2^2^2...
64, 128, 256, 512, 1024,
2048, 4096, 81...
You use this computer long?
I want to check my grades.
Oh, ahh, okay.
I'll just pick these up later.
[printer printing]
The school sends you one of those
electronic messages with your grades?
No, I use a password to log into
university's network.
Really?
Yes, since this hostel is associated with
the university's exchange program, this
computer is connected to their network.
This computer is part of
City Tech's network?
Yeah. It's one of only a couple of
computers that is off campus.
Man, things have changed since I was there
and we just had the one mainframe.
Well, don't let me hold you up.
I've got the password.
What?
The password to get on Tech's network.
It's time for some parallel computing.
What you talk about?
I figured out a way to check
all these other simple programs.
It turns out tech's got this
network of connected computers
that beats the pants off the mainframe
they had when I was there.
You went to City Tech?
Yeah, it was a while ago.
That's a great school.
What did you study?
Computers, symbolic systems, mathematics,
a little physics...
[upbeat punk music]
[camera flash]
[computer beep]
[repetitive keystrokes and computer beeps]
Amateurs.
[two computer beeps]
[typing]
[repetitive computer beeping]
[traveler grumbling]
Did you break the computer?
[French] That sound is annoying.
All right, just...
Excuse me.
[French] That is ineffective.
You are an idiot. What?
Just...
[mumbling]
Just give it one song and it'll
all be done. That's all I ask.
[synth pop music and computer beeping]
[singing out of sync]
[singing incorrect lyrics]
[8mm camera running]
What? It's beautiful. Oh, okay.
Piss off.
[computer beeping persists]
I am sorry to film, but it's so beautiful.
My other film is showing here on Sunday.
Perhaps you'll be here?
Ummm...
Possibly.
Excusez-moi, do you know why the
computer is covered by a blanket?
[computer dings and beeping stops]
I'm sorry. Some of the travelers were
complaining about the noise so I put the
blanket over it to make it quieter.
Is it broken?
No, no, no. I was just running
something. It's done now.
[French] Okay, never mind.
Excuse me one moment.
Listen, I have to ask you, you are able
to call the band just for to confirm that
they have correct address and
they are sending the check?
They're sending it. I mean,
they have the address here.
I have no way of getting in touch with
them, so I can't prove it to you.
Well, when is their next performance?
I forget. It's in a little
seaport south of here.
And the name of this band, it is...?
Why? You don't think they exist?
That's...
...Synthetic Re-evolution.
Okay, merci.
[band plays melodic computer music]
The main bar downstairs
is open until half four.
[French] Thank you. Have a good night.
[computer power button click]
[French] Thanks a lot.
[light switch click]
[repetitive mysterious music]
[suitcase latches springing]
[Russian] What are you doing?
What you do?
Oh, nothing. Just got to kick off a few
programs here real quick. Minimal coding.
You want?
I better not. I got to wake up early in
the morning before everyone gets in here
to work on some of these programs.
[exhaling]
Yourself is suited.
[computers booting up]
[computer wave beeping]
[repetive music grows in complexity]
Still running.
[music intensifying]
[computer wave beeping]
[water lapping]
[water lapping and wind flowing]
[computer wave beeping]
[water splashing]
[water lapping]
[typing]
[printer printing]
It's not just cell progression programs.
I mean, look at this type of program.
I ran 70,000 of this type before and
nothing of interest arose.
Then this one pops up.
Hmm.
I think it's universal.
Look at these programs. Rewrite systems,
two-dimensional cell progressions,
multi-way systems.
They all exhibit it.
Complexity arises out of simplicity,
but it's not your standard chaos theory.
Complexity isn't just injected into the
system. It just arises.
Why do you care?
Why is it important?
Because it doesn't make sense and it
should. You know, the real world is a
mess. War, relationships, love or lack
thereof... It's a miserable place.
If there's one place there
should be truth, certainty,
it's in mathematics, in logic.
Well, that does sound reassuring...
[Spanish] But I don't know,
that's the truth.
[mysterious tone and faint cheering]
Come on.
[Spanish] Yes...
Goal, Goal, Goal!
[Announcer] Oh, what a goal!
[Announcer] The rules are simple.
Put the ball in the opponent's net.
[Announcer] Don't use your hands. But the
sheer poetry that emerges sometimes is
[Announcer] just... Look at that again.
But that doesn't make sense.
But of course makes sense.
They have more shooting all game.
Only time matter.
No... Only matter the time.
Will you be here on Sunday?
They are having a screening of my film
and a little dance afterward.
Ah film, I make still photography.
You do? So do I. I just take
18 photographs in one second.
What?
I am joking. But ah, really, it's true.
They call film the moving image
but it never really does.
It only gives the illusion.
The camera takes 18 photographs in
one second... like this.
[hands clapping]
[intensifying synth choir tone]
[lamp rattling]
Are you going to be long?
We're just about to start a game.
There's the sign-up sheet at the bar.
[sigh]
Where's the sign-up
sheet for the computer?
Oh yeah, let me see.
People need to see this. I think
I just realized something huge.
Yeah, we've already seen it, mate.
I just need to print off some programs.
Ahh, voila.
Oh, shh...
[French] Oh my, it got all over you.
Ah, okay... I'm sorry. One second.
[coins rattling]
Okay... Use this to do a load of wash
and dry at the laundromat. Okay?
Thanks, but did you find the sign
up sheet for the computer?
[French] Yes, yes, yes.
Okay, computer won't go
anywhere. You're next on list.
[French mumbling]
Where's the laundromat?
It's by the arcade. We
are going there now.
Come on, we'll show you.
[sigh]
[tropical music]
[dryers tumbling]
[musician playing recorder melody]
[arcade game sounds]
Yes, yes.
Wooh, hahaha. Wooh.
Okay. Go up, go up, go up.
Oh no, let me do- Oowwww.
Yes. Yes. Yes, yes, yes, yes...
Oh, no.
[mysterious tone]
[tropical music]
[high heels clicking]
[dog barking]
[tropical music]
What the f- Son of a b-
My clothes are gone.
What the hell happened to my clothes?
Somebody must have seen something-
[Mandarin] Don't talk to me.
Ughhh...
Damn it!
What a crazy guy.
[mysterious computer music]
I thought you said I was next?
[French] Relax...
They'll be off in a minute, okay?
[laughing]
Hello. How did the wash go?
Somebody stole my clothes.
What?
Seriously. It's like they saw me coming.
Forget it. Can I get a porter?
Will that be cash?
Can you put it on Maxxie's tab?
He's a buddy of mine. He's in 2-B.
Maxxie, you're in 2-B right? 2-B?
Grazie, buddy. I'll get you back.
That's Maxxie in 2-B.
Hey... How's it going?
You staying here at the hostel?
[beer splattering]
[Russian] I didn't see the album.
[Russian] Never mind. Let's go.
Hey, coo coo. I think the
computer is open now.
Fuck it. Fuck it, Maxxie, you know?
No.
All I'm saying is got to stay focused
on what's important...
like getting those programs printed out.
Programs? Like the ones before?
Similar. I think I might have figured out
nature's secret for how it generates
complexity so effortlessly.
[repetitive keystrokes and music]
[printer printing]
[perforation ripping]
Maybe math isn't as general as we think.
Maybe the math that we use to describe
physics is just the path that human
civilizations just happen to take.
What?
I'm finding lots of systems where
complexity emerges out of very simple
programs, things that look like
snowflakes, fluid turbulence,
animal patterns, flocks of birds, DNA,
physics, biology, nature.
Maybe you can't reconcile the world with
calculus and continuous mathematics.
What?
Maybe there's one bit of small code, and
all this richness in the world
is just a consequence.
A program?
But it has to be simple and elegant.
It has to be highly compressed
in order to encapsulate all the
physical laws and complexity of biology.
It probably won't even be recognizable
at that level of compression.
Start making sense or
I'm taking back the beer.
Occam's Razor. Lex parsimoniae. Scientists
are always looking for the most simple
and elegant ways to describe phenomena.
Seemingly disparate ideas get unified
and integrated into a common theory that
are explained as sets of mathematical
equations. It's a similar idea, but
I'm looking for the most simple program
that explains it all. Maybe it's just a
few lines recursively executed.
A few... A few lines of code?
Sure, the idea is to minimize the input,
the program, and maximize the richness
of the output. The rules should always be
simpler than what they describe, or else
there's always a reason, the reason
itself, like adding axioms to deal
with incompleteness in mathematics. It's
the equivalent of someone saying "just
because" when asked for a reason. Have
you ever heard a Lagrangian interpolation?
What do you think, huh?
Want some?
Can I borrow that?
Yes...
Shit.
I'm, I'm not sure I...
Fuck it, all right. My point was you might
think this splattering of dots was random,
but there's always an equation of a line
that goes through these points, and
there's always a theory that explains the
results. So there's always a reason.
There's always a law if you allow them to
be so complicated. So what one strives for
is an elegant explanation. If it's not
small, simple, elegant, compressed, the
notion of a physical law becomes vacuous.
Hey-o, are you done with my pen?
So while traditional physicists are
looking for elegant mathematical formulas
based on differential equations, the
infinitesimal, continuous mathematics
such as calculus, I'm looking for the
one piece of digital code that explains
the universe. No measurement has ever been
taken with an infinite level of precision.
A digital, finite, discrete universe.
It's going to be a whole
new direction for science.
You've lost me... I... Maybe I'm just...
The problem is radical ideas like this
only get published and taken seriously if
they come from someone within the
establishment, someone with
some credibility. You know what I'm
saying? And I know just the guy.
Who?
He's got a background in program-size
complexity. He also won the Nobel Prize
for extending Gödel's
incompleteness theorem.
He's also knowledgeable in
the physics realm.
Who?
Dr. Mercury Jhaitin
If there's anyone who'll understand and
appreciate my work, it'll be him.
You know him?
Not really. But I'm going to mail him some
of my electronic messages, plus I'll also
mail him some printouts for reference.
He teaches at City Tech.
[computer wave beeping]
[quiet melodic music]
We need to discuss to check.
Look, I'm just as eager to get it as
you are. The band's good for it.
Synthetic Re-evolution?
Yeah...
Well, they are playing at
Que Sera Sera in a couple of days.
What?
I found a listing in the music
section of the paper.
What?
I found a listing in the music
section of the paper.
Really?
I want you to call the box office
and leave a message for the band.
What?
I just want to make sure that
they have the correct address.
Seriously?
[phone receiver picked up]
[phone ringing]
Here... Here, take it. It's ringing.
You dialed?
Take it. It's ringing.
Yeah, hi. Is this the ticket window?
Yeah, I have to leave a
message for someone.
Well actually, it's a band that's
playing there in a few days.
Synthetic Re-evolution... Okay.
[Mysterious ambient music]
Son of a- Some of my printouts are
missing. Did someone steal them?
[typing continues]
How long will it take you to run it?
Who knows? I'm thinking, I'm hoping that
it's a rather simple and elegant code so
when we start with the shortest programs
and check them in order of complexity,
hopefully it won't take forever.
Of course, there's the question of how
many steps will I need to run the program?
And how many steps will it take for me to
know that it's our universe or not?
And how will I know?
I need you to watch the computer while
I'm gone. You can let other people use
the computer, just, you know, make sure
that girl doesn't log on to the network.
Where you go?
I need Dr. Jhaitin's address. I can't
afford to just wait around for him to get
back to me. I mean, who knows if he checks
his electronic messages during the summer.
I'm going to Tech's campus. I'll get
it somehow. Somebody will know it.
[mysterious synth music]
[Cook] Hey.
[gorilla noises]
Is that Jhaitin?
Is that my shirt?
Ughh... What the...
What?
Most of the network computers haven't
run many programs at all.
They're running something but they're
not producing any output.
I wrote code to check, but
something's not right.
Great, first I run into Jhaitin and
don't get to talk to him. Now, this.
You saw him?
I think Jhaitin might be in cahoots with
whoever that guy was who stole my clothes.
I saw an exchange. I think it was Jhaitin.
It was definitely my shirt.
Now I have to deal with this.
Most of them are just spinning
their wheels on some routine
and aren't getting anywhere.
I wrote code that was supposed to check
that. It was supposed to check to see if a
given program would run indefinitely or
eventually come to a... halt.
[repetitive mysterious music]
Oh, my god, of course.
What?
Turing's halting problem.
Holding problem?
Halting, like, come to a stop. Halt.
Turing basically showed that there is no
easy and systematic approach to see if a
given program would stop or just keep
running forever until you had to start
banging on the keys to make it stop.
Escape. Escape.
It's directly tied in with Gödel's
incompleteness theorem.
Okay, here's a proof by contradiction:
Let's just suppose there was an algorithm
you could write to check to see if a given
program was going to stop. Then suppose
the algorithm was checking the program
that essentially said something
like the following:
If the Riemann hypothesis is true--of
course we would explicitly write this out
in a mathematical way--then do some output
and stop. Else, the Riemann hypothesis is
flase, do some loop. Of course, I'm
assuming the Riemann hypothesis is one of
the true and unprovable statements under
the current axioms of mathematics.
What?
Never mind, it just goes to show you how
difficult of a task this is going to be.
What task?
The task of searching for the code
that'll be the code for our universe.
This shows that there is no easy and
systematic approach to just look through
the space of all possible programs.
[Roy laughing]
Oh, Khatchig, you are so full of shit.
You know, Roy, if you would just stop and
think about things for just a second,
you might realize-
That it's all bullshit? Do you think
you're going to explain all the wonders
of nature and life with some rinky-dink
code? The world is made up of atoms,
not black and white cells on a computer.
You make a convincing argument, I'll give
you that, but I don't think you've fully
vetted your opinions for the actual truth.
You don't want to learn.
You don't want to listen.
Oh, yeah?
Maxxie, it's all right.
But he's always putting people down.
I'm only trying to help.
I don't need your help.
But I'm only trying-
Maxxie!
You got nothing better to do than poking
your nose in other people's business?
What makes you a physics expert, anyway?
What makes you? You don't
even have a university degree.
What are you talk about? He went to City
Tech, better than where you do study.
No, mate, he couldn't cut it.
He failed out.
It's not true. I didn't fail out. They
kicked me out. Who told you that anyway?
Don't you worry, mate,
just some little bird.
What you got, Einstein?
Eeee... Hiii-yah.
Hiii-yah.
Hey.
[grunting]
Stop, stop, stop, stop.
You're sticking up for the wrong guy, man.
He's a raging lunatic,
and he's not even your friend.
[faint typing]
Fuck you, Roy.
[Serbian] Unbelievable bullshit!
[exhaling]
You want?
Okay.
It's so stupid. Travka should be legal.
I guess...
Where is stuff no should be legal?
I do.
[ominous music]
I'm not sure-
Is okay. Talking is leave it to me.
You have identification?
We not stay long.
You stay here. He keep company to me.
Ha, ha, ha...
Ha, ha, ha, ha, ha...
You almost got us killed.
Relax.
Well, what did you get anyway?
[Russian] This.
Jesus man, put that stuff away.
Oh, Khatchig... Khatchig, American boy...
Come back here American boy
if you want some of my drugs...
Are you sure we're allowed
to be up here, man?
Relax.
It's my friend Maxxie. Maxxie.
What are you doing up here?
Um, um, I just came here
to look at the stars.
Here, take.
There's more from where that is.
[coughing]
Here, eat these.
You want?
[Russian] No?
Okay, how about this?
Hey, don't pressure him. He's a good kid.
Fine, you eat them.
Am I supposed to feel something?
One hour.
[trippy music]
[computer wave beeping]
[trippy guitar music]
[synth whoosh]
[bing]
[bing, bing, bing]
[video game beeping]
[frequency dropping tone]
[synth whoosh]
[beeping]
[computer wave beeping]
[intense trippy guitar music]
[video game boss music]
It needs to be simpler, simpler, simpler...
Jesus, Khatchig. Are you okay?
Khatchig... You should...
What are you doing in that shrub?
You have to look after yourself.
Come on. Come on.
[Spanish] Oh... Oh my...
Oh, get some sausage while they're out.
It's okay. Come on.
Just lay down, all right.
[spacey atmospheric music]
Are you okay?
Can you get my suitcase down?
I want to look at those printouts again.
Thanks, buddy.
Something tells me these
programs aren't simple enough.
There's too much built into them.
It needs to be simpler, more general.
Have you heard back from this guy,
Doctor um...?
Maybe it's useless anyway. Maybe these
programs won't tell you anything.
Maybe it's like the sieve of Eratosthenes.
He's Greek.
Yeah. Okay, just let me explain.
You start with a list of the positive
integers. Then you apply this very simple
rule to start eliminating all the numbers.
The numbers that don't get eliminated are
defined as the primes. But you know, a
physicist looking at something that
generated prime numbers in nature would
probably us a formula like n/log(n) to
make predictions. They would say something
like, "Look how statistically accurate the
model is. We can get it so close to the
right answer. Only off by two parts
in a trillion. It has to be right."
It is not?
No. The primes aren't statistical.
They're not probabilistic.
They're determined ahead of time. Remember
the sieve I was just telling you about?
Erat... uh... Erat-
Eratosthenes. Yes, the sieve generates
the primes. It's a simple rule, a simple
process, a simple program.
It's deterministic.
You know, a physicist's statistical
approach for making predictions about the
primes might be quicker and highly
accurate, but it's not the reality.
Predictions could be made exactly...
given the time to make the computation.
What you talking about?
Epistemology, the limits of understanding,
provability, incompleteness,
life, death, god, everything.
What?
I don't know.
Are you serious?
I think my main point was that even if I
could find the code, maybe it won't tell
us much. Maybe it'll just take too much
computing power to know anything.
Maybe it won't change anything.
I need you to do something for me.
What?
Can you kick off some programs?
Okay.
Can you also follow up
with Jhaitin for me?
What is this all about?
I guess I'm still holding out hope that
some of the stuff I'm doing matters,
that I'm making some sort of progress.
But, wh-
I appreciate your help on this.
[paper crinkling]
So if, if we live in a computer
simulation, what does this say
about the programs I will run?
That's the best question I've heard
anyone ask in a long time.
I just joking.
[sighing]
Let me know if you have any problems.
Hey.
How you feeling?
Okay.
Can I sit?
I found this downstairs by the check-in.
I mean, give me a break. Are you serious?
What?
[mumbling]
Are you kidding...
What?
This isn't for me.
Why do you say that?
Look, if you want me to take a
leap of faith, at least let there
be plausible evidence.
I mean, if you ask me to believe in the
Riemann hypothesis, I'd say, okay, I don't
know if it's true or not, but I'll take
your word, I'll go on faith. But this?
I'm just worried about you.
I'm through with drugs.
I'm glad to hear that, but
it's not just that, you know?
Do you think I'm crazy?
I never say that.
Well, then what?
Khatchig, you spend all your time on
whatever it is you're working on, but
with nothing to show.
No money, wearing the same stained shirt,
living off croissants and sausages you
stash away... not taking care of
yourself... it's no way to live, Khatchig.
It's not sustainable.
You know...
It's not about money, or a big
house, or two and half kids,
or whatever else makes
you happy. You know?
It's not always a straight path.
You know, maybe this is the level
I should be living at.
You know, the level that
makes me the happiest.
Are you happy?
No... not really.
Look... look, I appreciate it.
I appreciate your concern. I'll be okay.
I'll go get you some water. Okay?
[water flowing and ice ploping]
I'm worried about Khatchig.
I know. Me too.
Does he have any family?
I don't know.
We need to get him away from this
work of his for a little bit.
I mean, it isn't good to be so obsessed.
What do you suggest?
I don't know. Fresh air?
[space music]
Venice is supposed to be visible
tonight in the early evening sky.
Do you think there is life out there?
Intelligent life?
I don't know. But I think I will feel
even more alone if there was.
Why?
I guess it would just make me feel
more insignificant. I don't know.
It might be the mood I'm in.
I think traveling has this effect on me.
You ever heard of the Drake equation?
I don't think so.
It's the formula that estimates
how many planets with intelligent
life are in our galaxy.
Some people have estimated that there are
thousands of intelligent civilizations
in the Milky Way alone, but it relies on
a lot of things such as how many planets
are in our galaxy that are suitable for
life, the probability that life arises on
those planets, the conditional probability
that given life has arisen, the chance
that intelligent life capable of
producing technology emerges.
But the most suspect variable in the whole
equation is a fraction of a planet's
lifetime that's marked by an intelligent
civilization.
Because soon after intelligent life
emerges, it destroys itself with its
own technology.
So there is no one else out there.
It's probably hopeless. Just like
the current state of physics.
I mean, hasn't anyone heard of Zeno's
paradox? Reductio ad absurdum?
Digital physics is the only real hope we
have for absolute truth. Without it,
all we can hope to know is finite bits
in an infinite abyss.
The infinitesimal.
Do you believe it? Because I don't.
It's just an idea, and I find very
little evidence to support it.
Did you ever hear the joke about
the philosophers having dinner?
No.
Philosophers having dinner when one
notices the other one is not.
He, he just looks at, at his food.
Philosopher says, "Why don't you eat your
dinner?" And the other philosopher says,
"Because I'm not sure it exists."
"What?", he says.
"I only see the light reflects off the
food, and not the food itself. So,
so how can I be sure it exists?"
Well, the philosopher had no
answer, but he enjoyed his food.
And the philosopher who did not know that
the light reflects off the food entering
his eye implies the existence of the food
falls to the wayside due to hunger.
That joke really doesn't have a punchline,
and I'm not sure I get your point.
My point: What does any of this
matter, huh?
You think too much about all this nonsense
and you're the one who will be falling
in the wayside.
[Spanish] Yes. Me too. Very good...
Hey, don't you want to get some breakfast
while it's still out?
Mmmhh...
I brought you those printouts.
I thought you might look at them.
It's some of the results from
the program you asked me to run.
[subtle synth music with potential]
Oh my god.
I think this is the Riemann curvature
tensor used in the Einstein equations.
What? What did you say?
I think I'm seeing space and time
curvature in some of these results.
I have to check the numbers.
[bed creaking]
It's matching exactly. Don't you see?
See what?
It's just a network of connections
following an updating algorithm.
There's no notion of space or time.
General and special relativity
emerge out of almost nothing.
Ummm...
And special relativity holds too. Everyone
measures the same speed for light.
And these tangles in the network could be
matter. It's all just information.
We're getting it from bit.
But, but the world is made of atoms,
not points on a computer.
Well, this emergent phenomena might
just be the result of what's below
the Planck length and Planck time.
Did you ever think of that?
Of course not. I have no
idea what you talk about.
So who made the code? God?
Maybe. But maybe god's this high
school kid in a parallel universe.
You know, life may have meaning, but
we may just be helping to compute ten to
the trillion digits of pi for this kid.
This is...
I need to talk to Jhaitin now. I
reproduced Einstein's equations out of
out of almost nothing. General and special
relativity out of something so simple,
so elegant, it has to be right.
Don't you understand?
Not really.
So, so you found the program?
Well, no, but...
I found the class of programs.
If you take a node in these systems
and count the number of nodes that are
one node away, two nodes away, three nodes
away, etc. You know, that number grows at
a very particular rate. It's uncanny.
One of them has to be...
Jhaitin needs to see this.
Did you send Jhaitin these
programs or just the others?
No, just the others.
[printer printing]
I'm going to need you to send
those programs in an electronic
message to Dr. Jhaitin.
Can I have a beer?
Um, you have to drink
that beer at the bar.
Maxxie, sit down.
What, what are you...?
Uh, we are going to have to start charging
for all these printouts you are making.
Just put it on my tab.
Are these printouts for your big theory?
What's it matter?
The computer is for everybody's
use, not just yours.
Well, look, I wouldn't have to print
out so many copies if you had tighter
security around here. Someone stole
my printouts the other day.
Why would somebody steal your printouts?
I don't know. They're trying to steal my
ideas, pass them off as their own.
Nobody is trying to take your
ideas. Nobody wants your work.
Is that a beer?
No. Maybe.
I don't think that this arrangement
is working out anymore. Okay?
Look, just give me a little more time,
goddamnit. I'm working on something big.
I've narrowed down the space of all
possible programs to a specific
class of programs. I'm going to have to do
an exhaustive search of the subspace.
It's a huge task, but I mean, it's
feasible with access to this network.
The network?
Never mind. Just give me a little
bit more time. I'll prove it to you.
I have some really definitive
evidence right now. By this time
tomorrow, you'll have your money
and I will have been vindicated.
[repetitive driving music]
Hello, hello.
Hello. How can I help you?
I need to get in contact with Dr. Mercury
Jhaitin. Do you have his address?
Are you the one who called earlier?
No.
Well, I can't give you that information,
but if you give me a second
I can give you his name for
sending an electronic message.
I already sent him an electronic message,
and I doubt he checks it during the
summer. I need his address. I really
need to speak with him. It's urgent.
I'm not allowed to give out
faculty addresses.
Well, don't you have it
here in the computer?
I can't give out faculty addresses.
Fine, fine.
Well, do you have any literature on
physics classes you're offering
here in the fall?
I have a catalog with course descriptions?
Yeah, that'll do. I was
thinking about taking one.
All right, just a minute.
[intensifying driving music]
[thud]
Aawwwww... Ahhhhh...
[thump]
[gasping]
127 Tivoli.
Eeeee... Ahhh...
[door opening and closing]
[phone ringing]
Sorry... Hello? What?
Okay, hold on. Could you
go find Jacqueline?
Cause there's some guy from some band
who said he had a message to call her.
Okay.
Thank you.
Hello, Dr. Jhaitin? Yes, this is the
admin office. I'm sorry to bother you
but this is really important.
[balloon inflating]
Yes, Yes, I am trying to figure
out which train should I take.
Okay... Okay.
[Dutch] Mister.
Jacqueline needs to talk to you.
Just give me a little bit
more time. I've got it.
Uhhh... Fu-, I'm sorry.
I got to go. I can't...
[bird crowing]
[dog barking]
Shh. It's okay. It's okay.
Shh. It's all right, buddy.
I'm just here to talk some shop.
It's okay. I got something for you.
You see it? You see the sausage?
Huh? You see it?
Go get it.
I'm in.
[dog barking]
Oh, no.
What is that?
Oh, I think it's what that
phone call was about.
[dog barking]
How did you get in here?
Just hear me out.
[dog barking and scratching]
Oh my god. Do you want
me to call the police?
No, it's all right. Isn't it?
After all, I'm sure he's aware that
I didn't win the Nobel Peace Prize.
Just give us a minute.
[dog barking and scratching]
Euclid, come.
[dog yelp]
Thank you, Dr. Jhaitin. My name is-
I know who you are.
You're the one who sent me
your computer programs.
You got them?
Of course I got them. All of them.
Well, I wasn't sure-
I even printed out the programs
you sent me. They're right here.
Well, I just wasn't sure... I know
my work isn't very well organized.
It's not very well developed either.
Not developed?
Aren't you the one that broke the
particle accelerator at the university
a few years back?
I knew I recognized the name.
That wasn't intentional.
A lot of people in the physics
department were quite upset.
It set them back nearly two years.
So, what is it that you want
to discuss that couldn't wait?
Well, I wanted to discuss my work.
That's why you broke into my house?
That's why you nearly gave my wife a
heart attack? Because of your work?
I'm sorry, but I'm staying at this hostel,
and they're going to kick me out,
and I've nowhere else to go. And then,
then this work I'm doing...
I don't know if anyone else could
appreciate, you know, not without a
computer, math or physics background.
Well, don't you see the
implications of what I'm getting at?
What are you talking about?
I'm talking about my work, those programs.
What about them?
Well, did you even look at them? Did you
even read my notes, my work, my theories?
I mean, this could be a whole new
direction for science to go in.
This isn't science. It's speculation.
It's evidence.
I mean, look at it.
Are you telling me that time and space
emerging out of an even simpler concept
is just some sort of parlor trick,
just some sort of novelty act
you can impress ladies with at a party?
What kind of party would
you be showing this at?
I mean, I reproduce general and special
relativity out of almost nothing.
Did you even look at my work?
Great. A model with space, but it
has no notion of matter.
And unfortunately, we live
in a universe that has matter
and dark matter and anti-matter.
But matter could just be
like tangles in the network.
I don't think you understand
how science is performed.
What?
I'm serious. Your theories totally
ignore the scientific method.
What are you talking about?
I'm talking about the way science
has been performed for millennia.
You observe phenomena. You come up with
a theory to explain the phenomena. You
deduce what some of the implications of
this theory are, what the predictions are.
You test your theory against experiments.
If the experiments are consistent
with what the theory predicts,
this lends credence to your theory.
If not, you look for a new theory.
Well, that's the thing. Many things can't
be predicted. That's what I was saying.
You can't make precise predictions
on simple, deterministic systems.
It's like Gödel's incompleteness theorem.
There's no way to out-compute the system.
This isn't the same.
Do you know what Kurt Gödel once
said when someone at the Institute
for Advanced Study introduced
himself as an astrophysicist?
Enlightened me.
Gödel told him he didn't believe in the
natural sciences. He believed that the
nature of reality could be described
a priori, without the need for experience
or empirical evidence.
He also starved himself to death
because he thought people
were trying to poison him.
You're gonna tell me that this
is how the world works?
No, these are just the symbols that
humans have come up with to describe the
phenomena. Math is a human construct.
Some people would argue the contrary.
They'd say that math is discovered, that
it has always existed,
from the beginning of time,
in every corner of the universe.
We are just beginning to understand more
and more about it with each generation.
The real world is just information, bits
interacting, and what emerges, the
consequences, those are the physical laws,
and we describe it with this language
we've made up called mathematics.
Your model is deterministic.
You're trying to tell me there's
no such thing as free will? It is written?
Apparently, you're not a
Lawrence of Arabia fan.
But there's no to know exactly-
Where is quantum mechanics in your theory?
Where is Bell's inequality?
Where is quantum field theory and
the random, probabilistic nature
that we can show over
and over in experiments?
It isn't randomness. It's complexity,
irreducible complexity.
Nothing is random. Einstein was right.
God doesn't play dice.
So we should just rewrite thermodynamics?
Sure statistics and probabilities may be
our best tool at making predictions
because the complexity of the system is
just so overwhelming there's no way to
get to the final answer without
just letting it all play out.
But that doesn't mean these statistical
approaches are fundamental rules that
govern the universe.
It's scientific heresy.
So what? So was the notion of the earth
orbiting the sun at one point.
It's useless. You cannot put a man on the
moon with your science. You can't make
transistors with your science.
If you want to make progress-
You know, I used to look up to you
for challenging conventional wisdom,
but since you got your ideas out there,
you want it all to just stay the same.
My work was building upon other
people's work who came before me.
You're looking to rewrite all of
science. Advancements are made in
little increments.
I'm calling the police.
Don't bother. I'm out of here.
[security alarm beep and door closing]
Wait.
You show a lot of promise. You should
consider coming back to university
to finish your degree.
If you really want to be taken seriously
in the scientific community, if you want
to make a contribution, you have to
learn the standard model of physics.
Particle physics is an interesting world.
They're building the world's biggest
particle accelerator. Maybe you could
help discover a new particle.
A new particle?
Did you read anything I sent you,
you patronizing bastard?
[grunting]
[somber music]
[traffic passing and crickets chirping]
[cans rattling]
[somber music continues]
[projetor clicks, dog barks, bird chirps]
[dog splashing]
[dog barking, feet clomping]
What's that jerk doing?
Shhh...
Well, I think Jacqueline booked your bed.
Why did she do that?
She booked Lana's bed as well?
Sssshhhh...
You mean that girl that was here?
Yeah.
Yeah, I saw her packing her bags.
I think she left earlier today.
What do you mean?
You know she was going to a different
town. Oh, which reminds me,
Maxxie, from 2-B, he left a couple
beers on your tab before he left.
He said he knew you.
You serious?
[Dutch] Of course.
Why would I make this up?
You lied to me.
There was never any check.
I want you out.
Okay.
[suitcase opening]
Honey, are you coming for dinner?
I'll be there in a second.
[thunder rolling]
[record needle drops]
Do you want to dance?
Did you like the film?
Best film ever.
[thunder rolling]
Honey, your dinner is going to get cold.
Okay.
Honey... What?
No, it's...
I don't know.
[splashes, rain, thunder]