Wait.
I think we need to invest in a printer.
What do we need that for?
I thought we could print out some of the programs
and sell them at the merch table
or maybe use them as inserts for the next album.
Plus, we're going to need a faster computer.
I've got one of mine
that's going to give us enough juice to be able
to run all the visualization programs we need.
Speaking of which, I don't know
if you saw what happened out there-
Listen dude, I don't even want to know.
The band needs to conserve money.
We can't just keep paying for computer expenses.
But this is important.
There's something very weird going on here.
It's very counterintuitive.
Listen dude,
we can't just fund your computer hobby.
We got to do what makes sense for the band
and our music's the main focus.
So what are you saying?
Listen dude, we’ll
try to scrape some money together
to get some replacement parts
but we can’t just get a whole new computer
or a printer.
We barely have enough money
to get from gig to gig.
Hello?
Yes, I'm calling for a bed tonight.
You're ad says you
have a computer?
I'm on the east side of the city right now,
so I won't be there till later.
What's the best way to get there?
Ok
Hi.
How can I help you?
I called earlier today about a bed.
And how many nights will you be staying with us?
Indefinitely.
Indefinitely?
Voila.
Your bed is the left top bunk.
There she is.
L'ordinateur?
The computer
is only available a little while longer.
Hey, what you got going on here?
Appalachian Trail.
Hmm?
You will let me know when the check arrives?
Umhmm.
Sergey, just for to let you know I let the guy
stay in the left top bunk in the lounge
Just for a couple of days.
Just until he gets paid.
Ok, but you know what happened the last
time you were so generous, right?
I know. I know.